Hello, everyone, and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Catherine.
我是Catherine。
And today we're talking about money issues.
今天我们要讨论关于钱的问题。
That's right.
没错。
So there are some really interesting phrases and we're going to learn a little bit about
所以这里有一些非常有趣的短语，我们将学习一点关于
how money and social security works in the United States.
美国的钱和社会保障是如何运作的。
But before we get into that, why don't we look at vocabulary preview?
但在那之前，我们先来看看词汇预览吧？
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
So we're talking about retirement and that means we're going to talk about when you stop
我们正在谈论退休，这意味着我们要讨论当你
working when you're 63 or 65, how do you save money for that?
在63或65岁停止工作时，如何为此存钱。
And the phrase we've got here is retirement plan.
我们这里有一个短语是“退休计划”。
All right.
好的。
So a retirement plan.
所以是“退休计划”。
So as you say, that's some money that you have for when you retire, when you're 65,
就像你说的，那是你为退休准备的钱，当你65岁时，
when you're too old maybe to work.
当你可能太老无法工作时。
Exactly.
没错。
And there are many different kinds.
而且有很多不同的种类。
We're going to hear about one that's called a 401k.
我们会听到一种叫做401k的。
But we'll talk about that in a minute.
但我们一会儿再谈这个。
First let's listen to today's dialogue.
首先我们来听今天的对话。
Well, that was an interesting documentary.
嗯，那是一部有趣的纪录片。
For sure.
确实。
I didn't really understand some of the technical jargon they used in the film when they talked
我真的不太理解他们在电影里谈论美国社会保障时
about social security in the US.
使用的一些专业术语。
Like what?
比如什么？
Well, they mentioned how people put away money in something called a 401k.
嗯，他们提到人们如何把钱存到一种叫401k的东西里。
Yeah, I know it sounds weird, but a 401k is a type of retirement plan that allows employees
是的，我知道这听起来很奇怪，但401k是一种退休计划，允许员工
to save and invest for their own retirement.
为自己的退休储蓄和投资。
Through a 401k, you can authorize your employer to deduct a certain amount of money from your
通过401k，你可以授权你的雇主从你的工资中
paycheck and invest it in the 401k plan.
扣除一定金额并投资到401k计划中。
Everyone tries to contribute as much as possible so that when you retire, you can rest peacefully
每个人都尽量多存钱，这样当你退休时，就可以
on your nest egg.
靠你的“老本”安心休息。
That's interesting and logical, I guess.
这很有趣，而且我觉得也挺合理的。
In my country, we also have to contribute to a government run retirement fund, but most
在我的国家，我们也必须向政府管理的退休基金缴费，但大多数
people don't really trust it, so they just invest in properties or things like that.
人并不真正信任它，所以他们只是投资房产之类的东西。
That seems a bit unstable, don't you think?
这看起来有点不稳定，你不觉得吗？
Yeah, but corrupt governments in the past have created distrust among banks and financial
是啊，但过去腐败的政府造成了人们对银行和金融
institutions.
机构的不信任。
So now people prefer to have money hidden in a jar or a piggy bank.
所以现在人们更喜欢把钱藏在罐子或存钱罐里。
I've been thinking of doing that lately.
我最近也一直在想这么做。
I don't want some banker to run off with my money.
我不想让某个银行家带着我的钱跑路。
Alright we're back from today's dialogue.
好了，我们回到今天的对话。
Now some really interesting words and phrases there.
现在有一些非常有趣的单词和短语。
And as you said, this 401k, what is a 401k?
就像你说的，这个401k，什么是401k？
Well I'm not sure about the details, honestly, but the 401k plan is a plan for workers, people
嗯，说实话我不太清楚细节，但401k计划是为工人、那些
who are young and working, to invest in their retirement.
年轻且工作的人设计的，让他们为退休投资。
And so it's a way to save money.
所以这是一种存钱的方式。
So every day they put a little bit of money towards this plan and in the end when they
所以他们每天都会往这个计划里存一点钱，最后当他们
retire they will have a certain amount of money that they can use throughout their seniorhood.
退休时，就会有一笔钱可以在晚年使用。
Exactly.
没错。
And so before we have that, we have this conversation which starts with a documentary.
在那之前，我们有一段以纪录片开头的对话。
So they're learning about 401ks.
所以他们正在了解401k。
And in this case, the person says that they didn't understand a lot because there was
在这个例子中，这个人说他们不太理解，因为有很多
a lot of technical jargon.
专业术语。
Alright so this word jargon, jargon, it's very similar to slang, right?
好的，所以这个词“jargon”，行话，它和俚语很像，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
And it's a special kind of talking or special words related to a certain topic.
它是一种特殊的说话方式或与特定话题相关的特殊词汇。
Or a certain industry.
或者某个特定行业。
For example, you hear a lot of business jargon, right?
比如，你会听到很多商业行话，对吧？
Or marketing jargon.
或者营销行话。
Yeah, when people start talking about POPs and POS and all that jargon.
是啊，当人们开始谈论POPs和POS之类的行话时。
I lost you, sorry.
我没听懂，抱歉。
No, I don't get that.
不，我不明白那个。
Well jargon then is a special language for a certain industry or field.
嗯，行话就是某个行业或领域的特殊语言。
And in this case we're learning about financial jargon and investment jargon.
在这个例子里，我们在学习金融行话和投资行话。
So we're talking about 401ks and funds and all that stuff.
所以我们谈论的是401k、基金之类的东西。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
And now when they were talking about the 401k, he explained how they deduct money to put
现在当他们谈论401k时，他解释了如何扣钱来
into this plan.
投入这个计划。
Well, the question is who deducts money and where does it all go?
嗯，问题是，谁扣钱，钱都去哪了？
And so to deduct means to take away.
所以“deduct”意思是扣除。
And this means in a 401k plan, the government will deduct money from your paycheck and put
这意味着在401k计划中，政府会从你的工资中扣除钱，
it into a special savings plan for you that you can access when you're retired.
并存入一个特殊的储蓄计划，你退休后可以取用。
Okay, so to deduct means to take away, to take out, right?
好的，所以“deduct”意思是拿走、取出，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
So subtract, deduct, take away, take out.
所以是减去、扣除、拿走、取出。
Very good.
非常好。
All right.
好的。
And as they kept talking about money issues, the woman said that people in her country
当他们继续谈论钱的问题时，那位女士说她国家的人
distrust banks and financial institutions.
不信任银行和金融机构。
Okay, so you might recognize a word there, distrust, trust.
好的，你可能认出了这个词，“distrust”，不信任，“trust”，信任。
They have the same root.
它们有相同的词根。
And so to trust someone is to believe in them and to believe what they say.
信任某人就是相信他们，相信他们说的话。
But to distrust means to think what they're saying is a lie.
但不信任意味着认为他们在说谎。
Okay, so you don't really believe that person.
好的，所以你并不真正相信那个人。
No, so if someone says, trust me, I will take your money and I won't spend it.
不，所以如果有人对你说，相信我，我会拿走你的钱，不会花掉。
You say, I distrust this person.
你会说，我不信任这个人。
That means I don't trust.
那意味着我不信任。
Right, very good.
对，非常好。
And well, why do they distrust these institutions?
嗯，他们为什么不信任这些机构？
Because the government is a bit corrupt.
因为政府有点腐败。
Okay, so you hear this word a lot in the news or in the newspaper.
好的，所以你经常在新闻或报纸上听到这个词。
You can have a corrupt government or a corrupt politician.
你可以有腐败的政府或腐败的政客。
That means that the government does things but says it doesn't and maybe is dishonest.
那意味着政府做了事却否认，可能不诚实。
It's distrustful.
它是不可信的。
Right, so for example, a corrupt politician will support a law that's not really good
对，比如，一个腐败的政客会支持一项实际上不太好的法律，
but maybe he's being paid by somebody else.
但也许他收了别人的钱。
Or a corrupt politician will take money from the government institutions to use for himself
或者一个腐败的政客会从政府机构拿钱给自己用，
and not for the country or the people.
而不是用于国家或人民。
That's right.
没错。
So it's a corrupt, corrupt government then.
所以那就是一个腐败的政府。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
All right, so why don't we listen to our dialogue again and we'll be back soon with Fluency
好的，那我们再听一遍对话，一会儿回来进行流利度
Builder.
构建环节。
Well, that was an interesting documentary.
嗯，那是一部有趣的纪录片。
For sure.
确实。
I didn't really understand some of the technical jargon they used in the film when they talked
我真的不太理解他们在电影里谈论美国社会保障时
about social security in the US.
使用的一些专业术语。
Like what?
比如什么？
Well, they mentioned how people put away money in something called a 401k.
嗯，他们提到人们如何把钱存到一种叫401k的东西里。
Yeah, I know it sounds weird but a 401k is a type of retirement plan that allows employees
是的，我知道这听起来很奇怪，但401k是一种退休计划，允许员工
to save and invest for their own retirement.
为自己的退休储蓄和投资。
Through a 401k, you can authorize your employer to deduct a certain amount of money from your
通过401k，你可以授权你的雇主从你的工资中
paycheck and invest it in the 401k plan.
扣除一定金额并投资到401k计划中。
Everyone tries to contribute as much as possible so that when you retire, you can rest peacefully
每个人都尽量多存钱，这样当你退休时，就可以
on your nest egg.
靠你的“老本”安心休息。
That's interesting and logical, I guess.
这很有趣，而且我觉得也挺合理的。
In my country, we also have to contribute to a government-run retirement fund, but most
在我的国家，我们也必须向政府管理的退休基金缴费，但大多数
people don't really trust it so they just invest in properties or things like that.
人并不真正信任它，所以他们只是投资房产之类的东西。
That seems a bit unstable, don't you think?
那看起来有点不稳定，你不觉得吗？
Yeah, but corrupt governments in the past have created distrust among banks and financial
是啊，但过去腐败的政府在银行和金融
institutions, so now people prefer to have money hidden in a jar or a piggy bank.
机构中造成了不信任，所以现在人们更喜欢把钱藏在罐子或存钱罐里。
I've been thinking of doing that lately.
我最近一直在考虑这么做。
I don't want some banker to run off with my money.
我可不想让某个银行家卷走我的钱。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So on Fluency Builder, we're going to look at three phrases.
那么在流利度提升环节，我们要看三个短语。
So let's look at them now.
我们现在就来看看它们。
Fluency Builder.
流利度提升。
Okay, this first phrase is what the entire dialogue is about.
好的，第一个短语是整个对话的核心。
It's about putting away money.
是关于存钱。
So to put it away.
就是“put it away”。
Okay, so to put money away.
好的，就是“put money away”。
That's an equivalent of saving, right?
这相当于储蓄，对吧？
Exactly, to save.
没错，就是储蓄。
So in this case, to put away is a fixed phrase.
所以在这个例子中，“put away”是一个固定短语。
These words, they go together very often and it means to save.
这些词经常一起出现，意思是储蓄。
So you could say, oh yeah, last year I put away a thousand dollars.
所以你可以说，哦，去年我存了一千美元。
Okay, so you saved a thousand dollars.
好的，所以你存了一千美元。
Exactly.
没错。
Very good.
非常好。
And why are we putting all this money away?
那我们为什么要存这些钱呢？
We're trying to build a nest egg.
我们是在努力攒一笔“nest egg”。
Now this is a funny phrase.
这个短语挺有趣的。
It is funny.
确实有趣。
A nest is a home for a bird.
“Nest”是鸟的家。
You know, it's made of sticks and twigs and leaves.
你知道，它是由树枝、细枝和树叶做成的。
And a nest egg then has to do with a bird's egg.
那么“nest egg”就和鸟蛋有关。
Eggs in the nest.
巢里的蛋。
Well, I don't know.
嗯，我不知道。
I don't know where it comes from, but it does mean money that you've saved up for some date
我不知道它从何而来，但它确实指的是为未来某个时候
in the future.
存下来的钱。
So you could say, I'm trying to grow a nest egg.
所以你可以说，我正在努力积攒一笔“nest egg”。
I'm trying to build a nest egg so that in 10 years I can buy a house.
我正在努力攒一笔“nest egg”，这样十年后我就能买房子了。
Okay, so it's not only for retirement.
好的，所以它不只是为了退休。
You can build a nest egg to possibly invest it in the future into buying a house.
你可以攒一笔“nest egg”，将来可能用来投资买房。
Exactly.
没错。
It's your savings that you don't touch.
这是你不动的储蓄。
So I could say, I'm going to kill you.
所以我可以说，我要杀了你。
You spent the nest egg.
你花掉了那笔“nest egg”。
That's not for spending.
那不是用来花的。
It's for saving.
那是用来存的。
All right.
好的。
And well, where can you save money for your nest egg?
那么，你可以在哪里为你的“nest egg”存钱呢？
It's very popular to put it in a piggy bank.
把钱放进存钱罐很流行。
Well, maybe if you're five years old, but I don't know if I'd put a lot of money in
嗯，也许如果你五岁的话还行，但我不确定我会把很多钱放进
a piggy bank.
一个存钱罐里。
A piggy bank is usually a ceramic pig, you know, and it's got a hole in the top and you
存钱罐通常是一个陶瓷猪，你知道，它顶部有个洞，你可以
can put coins in the top.
把硬币从顶部放进去。
So we give these to children to teach them how to save.
所以我们把这些给孩子们，教他们如何储蓄。
So they can put one penny in every day.
这样他们可以每天放一分钱进去。
And then when they need the money or they want to spend it, they break the piggy bank.
然后当他们需要钱或想花掉时，他们就打破存钱罐。
Exactly.
没错。
You have to throw it on the ground.
你得把它摔在地上。
And it's sad because you realize, oh, now I don't have my piggy anymore.
这很伤心，因为你意识到，哦，现在我没有我的小猪了。
Lost my nest egg.
失去了我的“nest egg”。
All right.
好的。
So why don't we listen to this dialogue again?
那我们为什么不重新听一遍这段对话呢？
Let's keep a lookout for all these words and phrases and we'll be back shortly.
让我们留意所有这些单词和短语，我们马上回来。
Well that was an interesting documentary.
嗯，那是一部有趣的纪录片。
For sure.
确实。
I didn't really understand some of the technical jargon they used in the film when they talked
我真的不太理解他们在电影里谈论美国社会保障时用的一些
about Social Security in the US.
专业术语。
Like what?
比如什么？
Well, they mentioned how people put away money in something called a 401k.
嗯，他们提到人们把钱存进一种叫401k的东西里。
Yeah, I know it sounds weird, but a 401k is a type of retirement plan that allows employees
是啊，我知道听起来很奇怪，但401k是一种退休计划，允许员工
to save and invest for their own retirement.
为自己的退休储蓄和投资。
Through a 401k, you can authorize your employer to deduct a certain amount of money from your
通过401k，你可以授权雇主从你的工资中扣除一定金额
paycheck and invest it in the 401k plan.
并投资到401k计划中。
Everyone tries to contribute as much as possible so that when you retire, you can rest peacefully
每个人都尽量多存钱，这样退休时你就可以靠着你的“nest egg”
on your nest egg.
安心休息。
That's interesting and logical, I guess.
这很有趣，也很有道理，我想。
In my country, we also have to contribute to a government-run retirement fund, but most
在我的国家，我们也必须向政府管理的退休基金缴费，但大多数
people don't really trust it, so they just invest in properties or things like that.
人并不真正信任它，所以他们只是投资房产之类的东西。
That seems a bit unstable, don't you think?
那看起来有点不稳定，你不觉得吗？
Yeah, but corrupt governments in the past have created distrust among banks and financial
是啊，但过去腐败的政府在银行和金融
institutions, so now people prefer to have money hidden in a jar or a piggy bank.
机构中造成了不信任，所以现在人们更喜欢把钱藏在罐子或存钱罐里。
I've been thinking of doing that lately.
我最近一直在考虑这么做。
I don't want some banker to run off with my money.
我可不想让某个银行家卷走我的钱。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So this whole savings thing, are you good at saving?
那么关于储蓄这件事，你擅长储蓄吗？
Do you have your nest egg planned out for your retirement?
你为退休计划好你的“nest egg”了吗？
Nest egg, no, but I'm a compulsive saver.
“Nest egg”没有，但我是一个强迫性储蓄者。
Really?
真的吗？
I like to save a lot.
我喜欢存很多钱。
Oh, wow.
哦，哇。
Yeah, because you never know when you're going to need money.
是啊，因为你永远不知道什么时候会需要钱。
And I think once you get a kind of an adult job, you know, the nine to five job, it's
而且我认为一旦你有了成年人的工作，你知道，朝九晚五的工作，就
important to spend as little as possible so that you can create a nest egg or some kind
要尽可能少花钱，这样你才能为未来攒一笔“nest egg”或某种
of savings account for the future because it'd be nice to have a car or a house someday.
储蓄账户，因为将来有辆车或房子会很好。
Right, right.
对，对。
And also, as you say, unexpected things happen.
而且，就像你说的，意外的事情会发生。
So something may happen.
所以可能会发生什么事。
Maybe you break your arm and you don't have any savings or maybe no insurance.
也许你摔断了胳膊，却没有储蓄或没有保险。
So at least you have some money stashed away where you can use it.
所以至少你有一些存起来的钱可以用。
Exactly.
没错。
And I know that in America right now, in the news, the credit crisis is very popular to
而且我知道现在在美国的新闻里，信贷危机是
talk about.
热门话题。
And so part of this economic situation is that people owe more money than they have.
所以这种经济状况的一部分是人们欠的钱比他们拥有的多。
That means they've spent more money than they own.
这意味着他们花的钱比他们拥有的多。
And so they don't have any savings.
所以他们没有任何储蓄。
And that really scares me.
这让我很害怕。
So I think it's a really smart idea to start investing as soon as you can.
所以我认为尽早开始投资是一个非常明智的主意。
Very good.
非常好。
All right.
好的。
Wise financial advice from EnglishPod.com.
来自EnglishPod.com的明智财务建议。
Thank you.
谢谢。
All right.
好的。
So if you have any questions, any doubts or any more financial questions, please come
所以如果你们有任何问题、任何疑问或更多财务问题，请来
to EnglishPod.com and we'll see you guys there.
EnglishPod.com，我们会在那里见你们。
Bye, everyone.
大家再见。
Thanks for watching!
感谢观看！